<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD with OASIS Tables v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing-oasis-article1.dtd">
<!--Example of article with error in the NPG version (missing coid element) which needs to be fixed so that the corresponding author information can be linked to the correct author-->
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:oasis="http://www.niso.org/standards/z39-96/ns/oasis-exchange/table" article-type="nv">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">nrcardio</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Nature Reviews Cardiology</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1759-5002</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1759-5010</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">nrcardio.2011.135</article-id>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrcardio.2011.135</article-id>
            <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category">
                    <subject>nv</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="subject">
                    <subject>cardio_s7</subject>
                    <subject>cardio_s1</subject>
                    <subject>cardio_s3</subject>
                </subj-group>
            </article-categories>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>How should the appropriateness of PCI be judged?</article-title>
                <subtitle content-type="topic">Interventional cardiology</subtitle>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Stone</surname>
                        <given-names>Gregg W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1"/>
                    <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/>
                    <bio>
                        <p>Gregg W. Stone, MD, FACC, FSCAI is Professor of Medicine at the Columbia University Medical Center, Director of Cardiovascular Research and Education at the Center for Interventional Vascular Therapies at NewYork-Presbyterian Hospital, and the Cardiovascular Research Foundation in New York. Dr. Stone has served as the national or international principal investigator for more than 60 national and international multicenter randomized trials, has authored more than 1,000 book chapters, manuscripts, and abstracts published in the peer-reviewed literature, and has delivered thousands of invited lectures around the world. Dr. Stone, along with Dr. Martin B. Leon, is the director of Transcatheter Cardiovascular Therapeutics (TCT), the world's largest symposium devoted to interventional cardiology and vascular medicine, as well as numerous other annual courses.</p>
                    </bio>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Moses</surname>
                        <given-names>Jeffrey W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1"/>
                    <bio>
                        <p>Jeffrey W. Moses, MD, Professor of Medicine at Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons is the Director, Cardiovascular Interventional Catheterization Laboratory at NewYork-Presbyterian, Columbia University Medical Center and Weill Cornell Medical Center campuses. An internationally recognized interventional cardiologist, Dr. Moses has performed more than 15,000 interventional procedures, authored over 600 publications, and served as lead investigator for numerous national and international clinical studies that have demonstrated the effectiveness and safety of coronary stent placement. Dr. Moses is a Course Co-Director of the Transcatheter Cardiovascular Therapeutics (TCT) conference, and serves on the Board of the Cardiovascular Research Foundation in New York City.</p>
                    </bio>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="a1"><institution>NewYork-Presbyterian Hospital, Columbia University Medical Center and the Cardiovascular Research Foundation</institution>, <addr-line content-type="street">111 East 59<sup>th</sup> Street, 11<sup>th</sup> Floor</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="city">New York</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">NY</addr-line> <addr-line content-type="zip">10022</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="conflict" specific-use="yes"><p>G. W. Stone is a consultant for Abbott Vascular, Boston Scientific, and Medtronic. J. W. Moses is a consultant for Boston Scientific and Cordis.</p></fn>
                <corresp id="c1">G. W. Stone <email xlink:href="gs2184@columbia.edu">gs2184@columbia.edu</email></corresp>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="issue-date">
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="aop">
                <day>06</day>
                <month>09</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <volume>8</volume>
            <issue>10</issue>
            <fpage>544</fpage>
            <lpage>546</lpage>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-holder>
            </permissions>
            <abstract abstract-type="web-summary">
                <p>The appropriateness of percutaneous coronary intervention in the US has been examined from a large database of more than 500,000 procedures. The findings are surprising and, given their potential to be applied to quality-improvement initiatives, peer-review, and possibly reimbursement decisions, the proper interpretation of these results is essential.</p>
            </abstract>
            <counts>
                <page-count count="3"/>
            </counts>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <p>Every day more than 2,000 patients in the US undergo percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI), usually with the permanent implantation of one or more coronary stents. Few would argue that PCI is life-saving in patients with acute or imminent coronary occlusion, and substantially improves quality of life in patients with severe angina. Conversely, although procedural complications, stent thrombosis, and late restenosis have become relatively uncommon with the latest generation of devices,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1"/> the occurrence of these adverse effects can have serious consequences, and interventional cardiology procedures contribute substantially to the health-care budget. Thus, responsible physicians carefully weigh the likelihood that patients will benefit from such procedures. How are these decisions made? Approximately 30 years ago, physicians largely relied upon experience, intuition, and anecdotes to guide patient care. Since that time, we have entered an era of 'evidence-based medicine', characterized by reliance on randomized trials and observational studies to guide clinical decision-making. Professional societies expend great effort to synthesize thousands of studies into exhaustive clinical guidelines. However, many clinical scenarios are not directly addressed by the guidelines. From this void, 'appropriateness use criteria' (AUC) have emerged, in which diagnostic and therapeutic procedures for a range of typical patient presentations are categorized on an ordinal scale as 'appropriate', 'uncertain', or 'inappropriate'.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2"/> In 2009, a 17-member, expert panel of multispecialty physicians and researchers plus one health-insurance officer chose 198 distinct clinical indications (from more than 4,000 possibilities) and adjudicated the appropriateness of coronary revascularization on the basis of combinations of clinical symptom acuity, symptom severity, extent of ischemia, select high-risk clinical features, number of antianginal medications, and the extent of anatomical coronary artery disease.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2"/></p>
        <p>These AUC have now been used by Chan <italic> et al</italic>. to assess the appropriateness of PCI as performed in 1,091 US hospitals from data abstracted from the National Cardiovascular Data Registry (NCDR) CathPCI Registry.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3"/> From 602,781 PCIs for which data were submitted to the NCDR between July 2009 and September 2010, adequate descriptive elements were available to classify 500,154 procedures (83.0%). The vast majority of PCIs performed in patients with acute coronary syndromes (ACS, including ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction [STEMI], non-STEMI, and high-risk unstable angina) were considered appropriate, with little interhospital variability, whereas higher percentages of PCI procedures in patients without ACS were considered uncertain or inappropriate (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). In patients without ACS, the interhospital range of inappropriate procedures was wide, varying from 0% to 55% (median 10.8%).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3"/> How should these data be interpreted?<disp-quote content-type="pullquote" id="pq1"><p>...the vast majority of PCIs performed in patients with ACS ... were considered appropriate...</p></disp-quote></p>
        <p>Depending on the perspective, these results can be spun very differently. Some would emphasize that only 4.1% of PCIs in the US are being performed for inappropriate reasons, an extremely small proportion given the variety of clinical and angiographic presentations of coronary artery disease, the variability between hospitals, practitioners, and their local standards, and the lack of scientific evidence to guide all decisions. Even the authors of the AUC note that, for these reasons, a 0% inappropriate rate should not be expected.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2"/> Conversely, others might opine that nearly half of all nonacute PCI procedures are not being performed for appropriate indications. The proper interpretation of these results has important implications for quality-improvement initiatives, peer-review, and (potentially) reimbursement decisions by medical-insurance payors. Have we entered an era in which individual practitioners, hospital systems, and indeed an entire subspecialty can be graded and judged by such scorecards, thus diminishing or eliminating the need for personalized clinical decision-making?</p>
        <p>Understanding the limitations of the AUC and their application as applied through the NCDR is essential to address this issue. First, we can validly question whether the AUC represent an absolute gold standard&#x2014;are they the final word as to whether PCI should be performed? The AUC were determined using scientific evidence whenever possible, in accordance with the guidelines of the ACC and the AHA. However, only 1 in 10 of these guidelines is based on the highest level of evidence (from multiple randomized trials or meta-analyses); nearly half of the guidelines rely on expert opinion only, without meaningful, supportive scientific studies.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4"/> Moreover, the opinions of experts vary. Even among the AUC technical panel, only 70&#x2013;76% agreement existed in the appropriate and inappropriate categories, with wider variation in opinion among the uncertain categories.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2"/> When a separate panel of 85 cardiologists from 10 institutions reviewed and graded 68 representative indications, their disagreement rate was 66%; no physician achieved uniform concordance with the AUC technical panel.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5"/> Furthermore, even the authors of the guidelines do not always agree. For example, the ACC/AHA guidelines committee (and the AUC panel) consider PCI performed 12&#x2013;48 h after the onset of STEMI in an asymptomatic patient to be inappropriate or 'class III' (meaning that it should never be performed, is unhelpful, and might be harmful)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6"/> whereas, in the European guidelines, which were written by an equally esteemed group of experts after review of the same studies, the same indication is considered to be 'class IIb' (meaning that it can be considered).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7"/> The majority of the inappropriate NCDR cases after PCI in patients with ACS fell into this category. Equally informed physicians might weigh the implications of nonrandomized studies differently, such as the mortality impact of moderate or severe ischemia in patients with minimal or no angina, which is relieved more effectively by PCI than medical therapy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8"/> The 'uncertain' category comprises numerous such examples. Importantly, prospective studies of patient outcomes according to practitioner compliance with AUC have not been performed to confirm the validity of the criteria.</p>
        <p>Second, as acknowledged by the AUC panel, &lt;5% of all possible permutations of patient scenarios were classified and scored; many patients do not obviously fall into one of the three predetermined categories. Third, the AUC do not incorporate numerous essential data elements. For example, all stenoses with &#x2265;70% stenosis (or &#x2265;50% stenosis for the left main coronary artery) are considered anatomically important, but neither lesion characteristics nor the amount of myocardium supplied are considered. Few would doubt the great variation in the appropriateness of revascularization of a 95% ulcerated stenosis in a large proximal vessel compared with a 70% smooth stenosis in a small branch. The results of procedural physiological lesion assessment and intravascular ultrasound can substantially affect the appropriateness of PCI, but are not integrated into the AUC decision-making algorithm. Important clinical comorbidities are also not taken into account, such as diabetes mellitus, chronic kidney disease, cerebrovascular disease, or the likelihood of compliance with medications. Neither are patient preferences considered&#x2014;many patients prefer not to take numerous daily antianginal medications. Fourth, the guidelines and the AUC need to be constantly updated, but this process always lags behind reasonable practice. For example, PCI of left main disease is considered inappropriate by the current PCI AUC (published in 2009 and not yet updated), although the 2008 presentation and 2009 publication of the large-scale, randomized Synergy between PCI with Taxus and Cardiac Surgery (SYNTAX) trial<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9"/> resulted in subsequent revisions in both the US and European guidelines, endorsing PCI in selected patients with left main disease. Fifth, hospital data are recorded in the NCDR by persons of varying training and motivation; systemic monitoring of data accuracy is not undertaken. Finally, neither the AUC2 nor Chan <italic> et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3"/> considered the underuse of PCI (and angiography), which might be more harmful than overutilization&#x2014;for example, resulting in a lack of reperfusion in evolving STEMI.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10"/></p>
        <p>The authors of the AUC state that &#x201C;appropriateness criteria are intended to assist patients and clinicians, but are not intended to diminish the acknowledged difficulty or uncertainty of clinical decision-making and cannot act as substitutes for sound clinical judgment and practice experience.&#x201D;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2"/> The AUC are helpful to identify hospitals and practitioners in whom a closer look at procedural utilization is warranted, with the constructive goal of improving patient outcomes. However, neither the guidelines nor the AUC should be used either as a rubber stamp to sanction procedures or as a sharp knife to castigate a subspecialty consisting of care-givers who grapple every day with complex decisions in the best interests of their patients. Lastly, while outcomes are generally improved by application of guideline-based clinical-care pathways, an excessive reliance on 'cookie-cutter medicine', which requires patients to be shoehorned into preset categories, risks overlooking the unique diagnostic, therapeutic, and social challenges integral to each individual patient that must be considered for medicine to achieve its potential.</p>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <p>We gratefully acknowledge the insights on this topic provided by Paul S. Teirstein, Scripps Clinic and Research Foundation, La Jolla, CA, USA.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stone</surname>, <given-names>G. W.</given-names></string-name> <etal/>. <article-title>Everolimus-eluting versus paclitaxel-eluting stents in coronary artery disease</article-title>. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source> <volume>362</volume>, <fpage>1663</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1674</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patel</surname>, <given-names>M. R.</given-names></string-name> <etal/>. <article-title>CCF/SCAI/STS/AATS/AHA/ASNC 2009 Appropriateness criteria for coronary revascularization: a report by the American College of Cardiology Foundation Appropriateness Criteria Task Force, Society for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions, Society of Thoracic Surgeons, American Association for Thoracic Surgery, American Heart Association, and the American Society of Nuclear Cardiology endorsed by the American Society of Echocardiography, the Heart Failure Society of America, and the Society of Cardiovascular Computed Tomography</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Coll. Cardiol.</source> <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>530</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>553</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chan</surname>, <given-names>P. S.</given-names></string-name> <etal/>. <article-title>Appropriateness of percutaneous coronary intervention</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <volume>306</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>61</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tricoci</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kramer</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Califf</surname>, <given-names>R. M.</given-names></string-name> &amp; <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>, <given-names>S. C.</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Scientific evidence underlying the ACC/AHA clinical practice guidelines</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <volume>301</volume>, <fpage>831</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>841</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chan</surname>, <given-names>P. S.</given-names></string-name> <etal/>. <article-title>Concordance of physician ratings with the appropriate use criteria for coronary revascularization</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Coll. Cardiol.</source> <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>1546</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1553</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kushner</surname>, <given-names>F. G.</given-names></string-name> <etal/>. <article-title>2009 Focused Updates: ACC/AHA guidelines for the management of patients with ST-elevation myocardial infarction (updating the 2004 guideline and 2007 focused update) and ACC/AHA/SCAI guidelines on percutaneous coronary intervention (updating the 2005 guideline and 2007 focused update): a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <volume>120</volume>, <fpage>2271</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2306</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wijns</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names></string-name> <etal/>. <article-title>Guidelines on myocardial revascularization: The Task Force on Myocardial Revascularization of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and the European Association for Cardio-Thoracic Surgery (EACTS)</article-title>. <source>Eur. Heart J.</source> <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>2501</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2555</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shaw</surname>, <given-names>L. J.</given-names></string-name> <etal/>. <article-title>Optimal medical therapy with or without percutaneous coronary intervention to reduce ischemic burden: results from the Clinical Outcomes Utilizing Revascularization and Aggressive Drug Evaluation (COURAGE) trial nuclear substudy</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <volume>117</volume>, <fpage>1283</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1291</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Serruys</surname>, <given-names>P. W.</given-names></string-name> <etal/>. <article-title>Percutaneous coronary intervention versus coronary-artery bypass grafting for severe coronary artery disease</article-title>. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source> <volume>360</volume>, <fpage>961</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>972</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fazel</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name> <etal/>. <article-title>Choice of reperfusion strategy at hospitals with primary percutaneous coronary intervention: a National Registry of Myocardial Infarction analysis</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <volume>120</volume>, <fpage>2455</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2461</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
    <floats-group>
        <table-wrap id="t1">
            <caption>
                <title>Appropriateness of PCI procedures in the US<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3"/></title>
            </caption>
            <oasis:table frame="topbot" rowsep="0">
                <oasis:tgroup cols="5" align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                    <oasis:colspec colnum="1" colname="1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <oasis:colspec colnum="2" colname="2" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <oasis:colspec colnum="3" colname="3" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <oasis:colspec colnum="4" colname="4" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <oasis:colspec colnum="5" colname="5" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <oasis:thead valign="top">
                        <oasis:row rowsep="1">
                            <oasis:entry>PCI indication</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>'Appropriate'</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>'Uncertain'</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>'Inappropriate'</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>Total</oasis:entry>
                        </oasis:row>
                    </oasis:thead>
                    <oasis:tbody>
                        <oasis:row>
                            <oasis:entry>ACS</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>350,469 (98.6%)</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>1,055 (0.3%)</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>3,893 (1.1%)</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>355,417</oasis:entry>
                        </oasis:row>
                        <oasis:row>
                            <oasis:entry>Non-ACS</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>72,911 (50.4%)</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>54,988 (38.0%)</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>16,838 (11.6%)</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>144,737</oasis:entry>
                        </oasis:row>
                        <oasis:row>
                            <oasis:entry>Total</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>423,380 (84.6%)</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>56,043 (11.2%)</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>20,731 (4.1%)</oasis:entry>
                            <oasis:entry>500,154</oasis:entry>
                        </oasis:row>
                    </oasis:tbody>
                </oasis:tgroup>
            </oasis:table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
                <fn id="t1-fn1"><p>Abbreviations: ACS, acute coronary syndrome; PCI, percutaneous coronary intervention.</p></fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
    </floats-group>
</article>